<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
 <!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocActicle XML V4.5//EN" 
    "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
 <article id="acticle1">
       <title>South Africa Micro Model</title>
       <subtitle>Draft Working Paper </subtitle>
       <articleinfo>
             <authorgroup>
                   <author>
                         <firstname>Graham</firstname>
                         <surname>Stark</surname>
                         <email>graham.stark@virtual-worlds.biz</email>
                   </author>
             </authorgroup>
             <contractsponsor>Wider</contractsponsor>
             <copyright>
                   <year>2009</year>
                   <holder>Virtual Worlds</holder>
             </copyright>
             <revhistory>
                   <revision>
                         <revnumber>$Revision: 8140 $</revnumber>
                         <date>$Date: 2009-09-22 14:52:57 +0100 (Tue, 22 Sep 2009) $</date>
                   </revision>
             </revhistory>
       </articleinfo>
       <section>
             <title>Introduction</title>
             <para> 
             
             This paper describes a new microsimulation model of the South African tax system. The model is a not fully developed and could
             be improved in a great many areas; many of these are noted below. Nevertheless, it has some merits: a sound structure, use of
             the latest dataset, reasonably clear code, a comprehensive test suite, a powerful output system, reasonable speed and some
             interesting optional extras.
             
             </para>
             
             <note> 
             <title>Note: Preliminary Draft</title>
             <para>
             This paper a preliminary draft. It is missing some references, could do with many more examples of the model in use              
             and the language could be tightened up considerably. We will redraft as time permits.
             </para>
             </note>
       </section>
       <section>
             <title>Some Technical Details</title>
             <note>
             <title></title>
             <para>
                  (The reader can safely skip this if she is not reading the code along with this paper).
             </para>
             </note>
             <para>
                   The model is written in Ada, a conventional high-level programming language<footnote>
                         <para>
                               See: <ulink url="http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Programming:Ada"></ulink>
                         </para>
                   </footnote>
             .</para>
             <para>
                   About half the code was written specifically for this project; the remainder is common code to handle data, create tables, do tax calculations and so on. This code is used in a variety of projects <footnote>
                         <para>
                               for example: SLAS: A microsimulation model of the Scottish Legal Aid system: <ulink url="http://virtual-worlds.biz/demonstrations/slas/"> for the Scottish Legal Aid Board</ulink>
                         </para>
                   </footnote>
             .</para>
             <para>
                   Ada code is divided up into seperate units known as 'packages'; <footnote>
                         <para>
                               see, for example: <ulink url="http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Ada_Programming/Packages/">The Ada Wikibook</ulink>
                         </para>
                   </footnote>
             . in our case we have a package to define a household and perform operations on it such as uprating and reweighting, a package for storing results, a package for actually doing the calculations and so on.</para>
             
             <para>
             
             
             Compared to other languages often used for model building, such Gauss or Fortran, Ada is very strongly typed, and puts emphasis
             on being easy to read, sometimes at the expense of being a little long-winded to write. So, for example, an Integer is declared
             differently from a float, and there are special types such as enumerations (male, female or black, white, coloured), Integers
             which can only take certain values (an Age_Range might be 0 .. 140, for instance), Booleans and others. Much of the model code
             is spent simply defining things, (defining a household takes several hundred lines, for example); this can be tedious but from
             long experience we know that it makes the code much more maintainable and reduces the chances of bugs creeping in.</para>
             
             <note>
             <title>Child Packages and Filenames</title>
              <para>
                   One interesting feature of the Ada package system is that packages can have children. <footnote>
                         <para>
                               see, for example: <ulink url="http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Ada_Programming/Packages#Child_packages">this discussion</ulink>
                         </para>
                   </footnote>
                   . A child package has access to everything in its parent package. If a package has the name <package>Fred</package>
                   then a child package might be named, say, <package>Fred.Child1</package>
                   . However, since a period ('.') is used in most file systems to indicate the file type, in filenames the "." is replaced by an underscore, so the package filenames would be <filename>fred-child1.ads</filename>
                   and <filename>fred-child1.adb</filename>
                   The model makes heavy use of this feature. Almost all packages are children of a simple package <package>ZA</package>
                   which just contains some common definitions of datatypes, the model itself is a child of that <package>ZA.Model</package>
                   (<filename>za-model.ads</filename>
                   ; again that doesn't have very much in it directly, just some more common definitions) and the model components are children of that (<package>ZA.Model.Calculator</package>
                   , <package>ZA.Model.Results</package>. So, for instance, when we refer below 
                   to package <package>ZA.Model.Results</package>, the corresponding source files will be <filename>za-model-results.ads</filename> (the package definition)
                   and <filename>za-model-results.adb</filename> (the package body)</para>
              </note>
       </section>
       <section>
             <title>The Data</title>
             <section>
                   <title>The Income and Expenditure Survey, 2005</title>
                   <para>
                         The model uses data from the 2005 IES, the latest large sample dataset available for South Africa. <footnote>
                               <para>
                                     See <ulink url="http://www.statssa.gov.za/ies/publications.asp">IES 2005 Homepage</ulink>
                               </para>
                         </footnote>
                         . <programlisting></programlisting>
                   </para>
             </section>
             <section>
                   <title>Problems with the data</title>
                   <para>
                   
                   The dataset is extremely well documented, highly detailed, and up-to-date. However, for our purposes there
                   are some deficiencies which should be highlighted. 
                   
                   </para>
                   <formalpara>
                         <title>No Employment data</title>
                         <para> There is no data in the dataset on hours of work, employment status, disability, wage rates or other employment information. It is possible that such information is available in linked Labour Force Survey Data but due to time pressure (and emails not being replied to as yet) I haven't been been able to get a definitive answer on this. </para>
                   </formalpara>
                   <formalpara>
                         <title>No household relationship variable</title>
                         <para> Surprisingly, the datatset lacks a variable specifying the relationship of each member to the head of the household. Such a variable is included in practically every other household survey I am aware of. Without this, constructing family sub-units of the household is a matter of guesswork (see below). Fortunately, not much in the current South African fiscal system is based around such family units. </para>
                   </formalpara>
                   <formalpara>
                         <title>Reporting/Sampling/Weighting problems</title>
                         <para>
                               There are always problems with the representativeness of household surveys, but some of the problems with this one appear particularly acute. There is a useful table in the IES report <footnote>
                                     <para>
                                           <link linkend="IES_2005B">(IES 2005B Table 3, p 12)</link>
                                     </para>
                               </footnote>
                         comparing IES 2005 aggregates against National Accounts aggregates, and some of this is sobering, especially for non-work income. We return to this below. </para>
                   </formalpara>
             </section>
             <section>
                   <title>Reading and Representing The IES</title>
                   <para>
                         The code in the directory <filename>za/raw/2005/src/</filename>
                   are an interface to the raw IES 2005 dataset. The code here was mostly generated by parsing the schema documents accompanying the data distribution, with some hand-coding.</para>
                   <formalpara>
                         <title>COICOP_Definitions</title>
                         <para>
                               The IES classifies expenditures using the UN's "Classifications of Expenditure According to Purpose (COICOP)" <link linkend="UN2009">(UN 2009)</link>
                               definitions. The package <filename>coicop_definitions</filename>
                         contains a complete CIOCOP defintion at 3 levels of aggregagation, and methods to aggregate more disaggregated levels to higher ones.</para>
                   </formalpara>
                   <formalpara>
                         <title>Household Definition</title>
                         <para>
                               The package <filename>za-ies</filename>
                               contains a complete defintion of the the IES household. All items in the IES are included. Again, most of this file was generated automatically by parsing the main schema document <link linkend="IES_2005A">(IES 2005A)</link>
                               . All the categorical variables in the dataset are represented as enumerated types, for example, the following is our representation of the IES's gender variable: <programlisting> type Gender is ( missing, male, female, not_applicable, unspecified ); function Pretty_Print( i : Gender ) return String; function Convert_Gender( i : String ) return Gender; </programlisting>
                               Note the two accompanying function definitions, <function>Pretty_Print</function>
                               , which converts a Gender enumerated type into a human-readable format and <function>Convert_Gender</function>
                         which takes a raw string from the data and converts it to an enum.</para>
                   </formalpara>
                   <formalpara>
                         <title>Input/Output and Data Conversion</title>
                         <para>
                               The data was supplied as a series of normalised files in fixed-width text format (a default export format for the SPSS statistics package). The child package <filename>ZA.IES.RAW_IO</filename>
                               contains code to read these files, link the data using the Unique ID common to each file, and write the results out again in binary for faster access. <link linkend="IES_2005A">(IES 2005A)</link>
                         . Again, most of the code here was automatically generated from the schema documents.</para>
                   </formalpara>
                   <para></para>
             </section>
             <section>
                   <title>Testing the Raw Data</title>
                   <para>
                         The package <package>ZA.Tests</package>
                   contains some basic tests of the integrity of the parsed data. The dissagregated data is summed and compared to the results in the published report, and it matches. </para>
             </section>
       </section>
       <section>
             <title>The Model</title>
             <section>
                   <title>Availiable Information on Taxes and Benefits</title>
                   <para>
                         The South African fiscal system is very well documented. The Budget documents are particularly good. <link linkend="sars_proposals_2009">(SARS Budget Poposals 2009)</link>
                         gives lots of detail on the parameters of the current system, while the aggregate revenues we test against are mostly from: <link linkend="sars_rev_estimates_2009">(SARS Revenue Estimates 2009)</link>
                   </para>
                   <section>
                         <title>Taxes on Income</title>
                         <para>
                               Income Tax is well documented. <link linkend="sars_comprehensive_2009">(SARS Tax 2009)</link>
                               is a good simple overview. <link linkend="sars_comprehensive_2009">(SARS Comprehensive 2009)</link>
                               is a very detailed guide to the operation of income tax with lots of examples (despite the name, most of the information it contains seems to be from 2006). The test cases for allowances and deductions are derived from this document. <link linkend="sars_tax_stats_2008">(Tax Statistics 2008)</link>
                         gives a huge amount of detail on marginal tax rates, the value of deductions and sources of income, which we have barely begun to exploit. </para>
                         <para>
                               The operation of the Unemployment Insurance Fund (UIF) system is documented in <link linkend="sars_uif_quick_2007">(SARS UIF Quick Guide 2007)</link>
                               . However there is very little statistical information that I can find on UIF, probably because it is assumed not to be truly a tax. The most I found was one table in SARS <link linkend="sars_social_sec_2009">(Social Sec 2009)</link>
                         (table 6.5) which suggests our model is reasonably accurate in aggregate. </para>
                   </section>
                   <section>
                         <title>Indirect Taxes</title>
                         <para> 
                         
                         The operation is covered in <link linkend="sars_excise_2006">(SARS Excise 2006)</link>. Revenues are in the "Estimates of Revenues" document referenced above.
                         Current tax rates are in the Budget Proposals mentioned above. More details would be very welcome several areas,
                         detailed below.
                          </para>
                         <note>
                         <title>Indirect Taxes: Extra Information Needed</title>
                                 <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                                     <listitem>
                                                <para>
                                                Petrol and fuel taxation, especially maintained prices by province and the split between domestic and non-domestic production
                                                </para>
                                     </listitem>
                                     <listitem>
                                                <para>
                                                Taxes and duties raised on non-householders, probably expecially tourists
                                                </para>
                                     </listitem>
                                     <listitem>
                                                <para>
                                                Exemptions from VAT
                                                </para>
                                     </listitem>
                                     <listitem>
                                                <para>
                                                Retail Prices for excisable goods
                                                </para>
                                     </listitem>
                             </itemizedlist>
                         </note>
                   </section>
                   <section>
                         <title>Cash Benefits</title>
                         <para> 
                         
                         I found very little published information on the operation of the SA Benefits System. the <link
                         linkend="cape_gateway_2009">Cape Gateway</link> and the <link linkend="sassa_2009">SASSA Website</link> both have
                         some information including all current rates, but I've yet to find anywhere a detailed description of the
                         means-test used for Pensions and Child Support. <link linkend="sars_social_sec_2009">SARS Social Sec 2009</link>
                         is a good source for caseloads and expenditures.
                         
                         </para>
                   </section>
             </section>
             <section>
                   <title>Unit Tests</title>
                   
                   <para> The model already has a fairly comprehensive unit test suite, though much could be done. Unit testing is a method
                   which attempts to test if individual units of code (procedures and functions) are suitable for purpose 
                   <footnote> <para>For more on unit testing in general, see: <ulink
                   url='http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unit_testing'>Wikipedia</ulink> </para> </footnote> 
                   
                   Much of my understanding of the IES dataset and the South African fiscal system is embodied in its test suite. Much of
                   the calculation code was developed 'test first': write the unit tests expressing (for example) how the health allowances
                   available in the Income Tax system should respond to changes to income or spending on health, and then write just enough
                   program code to make the tests pass.
                   
                   </para>
                   
                   <para>
                   Package <package>ZA.Tests</package>
                   contains tests of the original dataset, including (mostly successful) attempts to reconstruct some of the tables
                   in the IES report documentation.
                   
                   </para>
                   <para>
                   
                   Package <package>ZA.Model.Calculator.Tests</package> contains a test suite for the calculations and parameter system. If
                   you want to verify what the model actually does when it calculates taxes and benefits, this is a good place to start.
                   
                   </para>
             </section>
             <section>
                   <title>Model Data Set</title>
                   <para>
                         Model data set defined in two packages <package>ZA.Model_Types</package>
                         , which contains definitions and <package>ZA.Model.Data</package>
                         which defines the structure of a household and provides some basic <function>To_String</function>
                         procedures for printing. A Child package <package>ZA.Model.Data.Binary_IO</package>
                         allows wrting of households out to disk as binary images and random-access reads to them. The model dataset of 21,144 households can be read in approximately 3 seconds on the author's development server <footnote>
                               <para>(HP ML118 with Dual-Core AMD Opteron 1210 (1.8 GHz) processor).</para>
                         </footnote>
                   ; the completed model takes 37 seconds on the same machine for a complete 2-system run. </para>
                   <para> Each household is structured into a series of family units, each containing adults and children. This is standard procedure but problematic in this case because the IES has no 'relation to head of household' variable which would normally be used. This is discussed below. </para>
                   <para> Large number of codes dropped, esp possession of durables. Some codes cleaned up ('don't knows' mapped to 'others'). For incomes and expenses, use level 2 COICOP codes. For expenditures, level 3 (this aggregates over some interesting things e.g. all tobacco treated as cigarettes). No uprating and grossing up at this stage. </para>
                   <para>
                         Program <package>ZA.Model.Dataset_Maker</package>
                   maps from the raw dataset to the model one. </para>
                   <para>
                         Tests in <filename>???</filename>
                   confirm CHECK AGAIN no damage done to data at this stage. </para>
                   <formalpara>
                         <title>Problem 1: No Relationship to Head Variable</title>
                         <para> Allocation to families based on guesswork (but may not matter that much given SA fiscal rules). People partnered off to people of opposite sex near them in age, children allocated to couples, then single females. </para>
                   </formalpara>
                   <formalpara>
                         <title>Problem 2: Expenses and Some Incomes Aggregated To Household Level</title>
                         <para> Presently, all these are allocated to single 'richest' person of working age. </para>
                   </formalpara>
                   <formalpara>
                         <title>Problem 3: Ages In Bands</title>
                         <para> 5 - Year bands. People allocated randomly to each year. Wrong for very young (child mortality) and very old </para>
                   </formalpara>
                   <formalpara>
                         <title>Problem 4: No Labour Supply Information</title>
                         <para> Costs of working (transport, etc.) Hours of work Employment Status Query: does the labour force survey re-interview same people? </para>
                   </formalpara>
             </section>
             <section>
                   <title>Model Structure</title>
                   <para> Since the model is organised into a series of relatively independent packages, all with reasonably clean interfaces, it's quite easy to assemble the packages into a variety of specialist forms, for example as a component of a macro-to-micro model, or a labour supply simulator, or an online Budget calculator. </para>
                   <para>
                         The default model code is conventionally structured tax-benefit model with two (pre- and post-) sets of parameters and a fixed set of outputs. The main 'driver' module for this is <package>ZA.Model.Runner</package>
                         Since the model was initialy developed as part of the Wider <link linkend="wider_2009">(WIDER 2009)</link>
                         project, the package <package>ZA.Model.Wider-Runner</package>
                   provides a customised version with input and output procedures tailored to the somewhat restricted requirements of that site, with output being produced in a comma-delimited-ascii format common to all the Wider models and a simple text input procedure for the parameters. </para>
             </section>
             <section>
                   <title>Weighting and Uprating</title>
                   <para> Two related sets of corrections are applied to the data. Firstly, the data is reweighted so that it better resembles other known facts about the South African economy, and better predicts some economic aggregates. Secondly, it is uprated it so as to capture changes in the economy between the sample period and the present day. Related to this, probabilistic take-up corrections are applied to modelled state benefit entitlements; this is discussed in a subsequent section. </para>
                   <section>
                         <title>Uprating</title>
                         <para>
                               The IES Data was collected during September 2005 to August 2006. <link linkend="IES_2005C">(IES 2005C, p 1)</link>
                               . The procedure <function>Uprate</function>
                               in <package>ZA.Model.Data</package>
                               applies some simple uprating to the data, to move the data to the latest date available<footnote>
                                     <para>At the time of writing this is May 2009</para>
                               </footnote>
                               . Wages and incomes are moved in line with changes in employee compensation per capita <footnote>
                                     <para>
                                           From <ulink url="http://www.statssa.gov.za/publications/P0441/P04411stQuarter2009.pdf"></ulink>
                                     </para>
                               </footnote>
                               . Everything else (including non-work income and expenses and consumption is moved with nominal GDP per capita <footnote>
                                     <para>
                                           <ulink url="http://www.statssa.gov.za/publications/statsdownload.asp?PPN=P0141&amp;SCH=4411"></ulink>
                                     </para>
                               </footnote>
                               . Presently, macroeconomic values are hard-coded into the program. All incomes and expenditures are moved from an assumed base of March 2006, which is correct for the annualised version of IES expendures but not for incomes <link linkend="IES_2005A">(IES 2005A p53)</link>
                         . Consequently, at the moment we over-inflate the incomes of later-interviewed households and under-inflate earlier ones. </para>
                         <note>
                               <title>Uprating Todo</title>
                               <para>Apply different factors depending on interview month;</para>
                               <para>Think about more appropriate indices?</para>
                               <para>Move Macro information to an external file so it can be changed without recompilation.</para>
                         </note>
                   </section>
                   <section>
                         <title>Re-weighting</title>
                         <para>
                               The procedure <function>Apply_Income_Consumption_Adjustments</function>
                               in package <package>ZA.Model.Data</package>
                         contains code to reweight the data so that: </para>
                         <orderedlist spacing="compact">
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> It better resembles national accounts aggregates; </para>
                               </listitem>
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> The model's predictions better match reported aggregates for revenues and payments; and </para>
                               </listitem>
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> Population growth since 2005/6 is accounted for. </para>
                               </listitem>
                         </orderedlist>
                         <para> This routine probably needs more work than any other. 1) and 2) may at times work against each other. The only change made to the supplied weights is a uniform increase to reflect population growth; all other changes are multipliers applied to the recorded incomes and consumption data, as if all differences are due to under-reporting by the households that are in the sample; this is a reasonably standard assumption [REF IFS Model WP] but could cause highly misleading results if (as seems likely) there is instead significant under-sampling of some types of household. </para>
                         <para>
                               Most of the weights are derived from Statistics South Africa's comparison of aggregate IES data with National Accounts data<link linkend="IES_2005B">(IES 2005B Table 3, p 12)</link>
                         . [REF SPI Adjustment] This table suggests a huge under reporting of non-work income, especially dividend income. However, applying the multipliers implied to this table produces a huge over-estimate of total income tax revenues, of the order of 50%. Consequently, the multipliers used for investment income have been scaled back so as to give an approximately correct value for aggregate income tax revenue. Likewise expenditures on excisable goods (except petrol) are scaled to give approximately correct revenues. </para>
                         <note>
                               <title>Re-Weighting: To Do</title>
                               <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                                     <listitem>
                                           <para> Use CALMAR to produce better weights for (at least) number of disabled, population structure changes since 2006; </para>
                                     </listitem>
                                     <listitem>
                                           <para>
                                                 Understand <link linkend="IES_2005B">(IES 2005B Table 3, p 12)</link>
                                           better. Are the categories the same? </para>
                                     </listitem>
                                     <listitem>
                                           <para>
                                                 Do a detailed comparison of the model tax against the tables in <link linkend="sars_tax_stats_2008">(SARS Tax 2008)</link>
                                           . Check split between earned/unearned income, value of expenses, distribution of marginal rates. </para>
                                     </listitem>
                               </itemizedlist>
                         </note>
                         <section>
                               <title>Pitfalls of Re-Weighting Survey Data</title>
                               <para> The procedure described above is probably no worse than that used in many tax-benefit models, but it seems to me that there are dangers in applying any re-weighting procedure indiscriminately. Data from sample surveys can suffer from response bias [REF], so certain types of people or households are less likely to respond, and from under-reporting[REF], so those households that do respond report less spending on, say, tobacco, or receiving less investment income than they really have. Further, the sample universe can exclude significant groups of people: since the IES is a household sample it doesn't cover, for example, people living in hostels, prisons or hospitals, nor does it cover consumption by tourists. Response bias can be corrected for by re-weighting the data; the IES data is supplied with weights which correct for some differences between the raw sample population and known aggregate data [REF], using the CALMAR [REF] program [CHECK], but not others that may be important; for example, the disabled and the very rich are typically less likely to respond to sample surveys [REF]. Under reporting can be corrected, to a degree, by inflating the reported incomes and expenditures of the households that do respond (so those who drink beer can be imputed to drink twice as much as they claim, for example). These two kinds of corrections can easily be used to produce apparently perfect predictions of total revenues or caseloads, and indeed the model does this in some places. But it is important to realise that the cost of this may be the worsening of the models estimates of more important things than revenue estimates, such as the distributional effects of tax change. For example suppose that calculations based on the data generate half the revenue from taxes on beer as is actually the case. Plainly, assuming that the cause was under-reporting (perhaps because people were embarrassed about drinking all that beer), and so doubling all the recorded beer expenditures would fix this. But if, in fact, the reason for the low prediction was that the survey had under-sampled beer drinkers (perhaps because a lot of beer was drunk by non-householders, for example those in hostels or in the army) then we might be worsening our model of the distributional impact of any change in beer taxes, since, should these taxes be increased, we would be report over-large losses for those households who did report beer consumption, instead of reporting a larger amount of smaller losses. </para>
                               <para> Further, with reweighting it is always possible for your model to produce apparrently perfect answers, no matter how many mistakes there are in the underlying code. </para>
                         </section>
                   </section>
             </section>
             <section>
                   <title>Calculation Section</title>
                   <para>
                         The object of the calculation section is to produce one record of results for one household, given one set of parameters describing the tax system. The design is kept as clean as possible: all the work in retrieving, uprating and re-weighting a household takes place upstream of the calculation modules<footnote>
                               <para>with the exception, arguably, of takeup corrections; these are discussed below.</para>
                         </footnote>
                   and all the output routines are downstream. This design allows for much easier testing, since it's easy to construct simplified households that stress one part of the tax system, and because the results easily checked since the formal results (tax due, benefits entitled to) are presented independently of any aggregation or re-weighting. Several packages collaborate in this </para>
                   <para> Presently, the system modelled is a fairly literal interpretation of the current South African system. Very significant changes, for example treating husbands and wives jointly for Income Tax purposes, would require re-programming. Nonetheless quite a large variety of changes can be modelled; for example, the income definitions for taxable incomes or benefit means-tests can be varied arbitrarily and the means-tested benefits can be made subject to a gradual taper rather than an instant cut-off. </para>
                   <section>
                         <title>Parameters Packages</title>
                         <para>
                               The package <package>ZA.Model.Parameters</package>
                               defines a set of records defining the tax system. Each tax and benefit is defined in its own record. There is a routine to uprate the entire system <footnote>
                                     <para> though this hasn't been completed as of 07/09/2009</para>
                               </footnote>
                               The child package <package>ZA.Model.Parameters.Defaults</package>
                               provices a method to retrieve a default set of parameters for different fiscal years<footnote>
                                     <para> as of 07/09/2009 only the 2009 system is complete.</para>
                               </footnote>
                               . The child package <package>ZA.Model.Parameters.Wider</package>
                         provides a simple read routine for a restricted set of parameters that can be changed using the Wider front-end. </para>
                         <section>
                               <title>Indirect Tax Parameters</title>
                               <para>
                                     The figures we use for the selling prices of goods are derived from the assumed shares of taxes in the selling prices of goods taken from <link linkend="sars_proposals_2009">(SARS Budget Proposals 2009, p 12,13 "Customs and Excise Duties")</link>
                               . It's possible that these prices are in fact too high, particularily for alcohol bought in bulk, and this may explain some of the underestimation of excise duties in the un-grossed model results. </para>
                         </section>
                   </section>
                   <section>
                         <title>Results Packages</title>
                         <para>
                               The package <package>ZA.Model.Results</package>
                               defines a single output from the calculation package for one household. The structure of the main <structname>Household_Result</structname>
                               record closely follows the structure imposed on the model household. Routines are provided to calculate two definitions of income <termdef>disposable income</termdef>
                               , which excludes indirect taxes and <termdef>net income</termdef>
                               , which includes them these and other aggregates are calculated for the household as whole, for family units within the household and for individuals <footnote>
                                     <para>Net (after indirect tax) income is calculated for the household only, since it is not possible to assign expenditures to individuals.</para>
                               </footnote>
                         . </para>
                   </section>
                   <section>
                         <title>The Calculator</title>
                         <para>
                               The package <package>ZA.Model.Calculator</package>
                         contains the actual tax and benefit calculations. In future it may be necessary to split this package into child packages for Income Tax, Benefits, etc.. With a few exceptions (and assuming the reader can read Ada code) the code should be reasonably self-explanatory. </para>
                         <para>
                               Development was constrained by time constraints and hampered by lack of detail, particularily concrete examples that could be converted into test cases. Particular areas of worry are the cash benefits means tests, where I could find almost no detail on what counted as income (all household income or family unit income, for instance) and the deductions and exemptions from income tax, where <link linkend="sars_comprehensive_2009">(SARS Comprehensive 2009)</link>
                               gives good examples of how components of the tax system work <footnote>
                                     <para>
                                           See for instance <link linkend="sars_comprehensive_2009">(SARS Comprehensive 2009, Section 7.5 p 30)</link>
                                     for a discussion of how health deductions work </para>
                               </footnote>
                         but few examples of the operation of the system as a whole. Much work therefore needs to be done on creating a more comprehensive test and example suite for the calculation section. </para>
                         <para>
                               The package <package>ZA.Model.Calculator.Tests</package>
                               provides a suite of unit tests for each of the modelled taxes and benefits <package>ZA.Model.Calculator</package>
                         's, all of which pass. However, this doesn't provide proof that the procedures correctly model the relevant taxes, only that they correctly model my specification of them (no implementation errors, but possibly specification errors). Nonetheless the tests tests provide useful documentation on what it was believed each routine should do, and a test of whether it actually does those things. </para>
                         <para> The calculation code was quite hastily written and could eventually do with a cleanup and re-organisation. The handling of incomes is unnessarily complicated, for example, and some of the means-test code is awkward. </para>
                         <section>
                               <title>Modelling Benefits</title>
                               <para> The two major means-tested benefits, Child Support and Old Age Pensions, have relatively simple rules and are straightforward to model, with the exception of the means-tests themselves. So far, I have no information on precisely what counts as income; for example, does the income of every member of the household count, or just the family unit of the claimant (so if an elderly woman with no income lives with her children who have employment income, does that employment income count towards the means-test?). The assumption at the moment is that only family income counts; ideally this would be parameterised so the user could switch between different aggregation levels. </para>
                               <para> The IES has no information on the disability status of household members. Consequently we model Disability Grants simply by assigning a grant to anyone who is recorded as having one in the raw data. This is problematic since it is likely [REF] that households with disabled members will be undersampled in a relatively onerous survey such as the IES, and the weighting scheme used is unlikely to fully correct for this. </para>
                         </section>
                         <!-- modelling benefits -->
                         <section>
                               <title>Poverty State</title>
                               <para>
                                     A household's poverty state is calculated using poverty lines taken from <link linkend="treas_poverty">(Treasury 2007)</link>
                               . This describes a simple 'fixed amount per person' poverty line. The poverty line is treated as a model run-setting (so common to both (or all) the scenarios in a run). The routine is very simple and would need adapting for more complex poverty lines which have different allowances for different household members. Likewise (SARPN 2007) suggests two poverty lines, 'extreme' and 'moderate', but we only use the moderate one at present, and hence have a simple 'in poverty', 'not in poverty' outcome. </para>
                         </section>
                         <!-- modelling benefits -->
                         </section>
                   <!-- the calculator -->
                   <section>
                         <title>Takeup Corrections</title>
                         <para>
                               Running the model as described up to this point, using the actual 2009/10 tax and benefit parameters, produces large over estimates of costs and caseloads for Pensions and Child Support but a large under-estimate of disability grants. <footnote>
                                     <para>
                                           Benefit costs and caseloads are from <link linkend="sars_social_sec_2009">SARS Social Sec 2009</link>
                                     , tables 6.3 and 6.4.</para>
                               </footnote>
                         . Pension takeup is modelled 78%, Child Support 71%, whilst Disability Grants are understated by 40%. As is common in tax-benefit models, the over-estimate of Pension and Child Support is treated here as non-takeup and the under-estimate of Disability as a sampling problem. </para>
                         <para> One approach to correcting this would simply be to re-weight the data we do have (so multiplying all Child Support entitlements by 0.71 and all Disability Grants by 1.4). This would produce correct values for benefit expenditure, but wouldn't correct caseload estimates and, more importantly, would get the distributional impact of these benefits wrong since we would be modelling the effects of a large number of low entitlements spread widely, instead of the reality of a smaller number of large entitlements claimed by a proportion of the entitled households. </para>
                         <para>
                               There is a large literature on benefit takeup, mainly from developed counties <footnote>
                                     <para>
                                           See <link linkend="fry_and_stark_1993">Fry and Stark 1993</link>
                                     [EXPAND THIS, ADD IFS SURVEY, DWP]</para>
                               </footnote>
                         , including a number of behavioural studies which attempt to predict the likelihood of a family claiming benefits, given their demographic characteristics, their other income and the amount of benefit to which the family is entitled. </para>
                         <para>
                               There hasn't been time to produce a full behavioural study of benefit takeup here, though it would make an interesting project. As an interim solution, a simple probabilistic correction is applied to each apparently entitled household. So, since there is 71% modelled takeup of Child Support, the routine sets entitlement to zero for 29% of households, with these households being selected randomly during each run. Code for this is in the package <package>ZA.Model.Takeup</package>
                         . My guess is that takeup is likely to vary significantly by, for example, rural/urban location, so our approach is likely to be misleading, but is the least bad solution in the available time. </para>
                         <para> Unlike (for instance) the corresponding benefits in the UK, the amount of Child Support and Pension due in South Africa does not decline gradually with income; instead, they are 'all or nothing'. Since the evidence is that small entitlements are taken up less frequently than large ones, this makes our simple correction slightly less bad than it would be in countries with a more sophisticated benefit system. </para>
                   </section>
                   <!-- takeup -->
                   <section>
                         <title>Labour Supply and Incentives</title>
                         <para> The model has two features that would make it useful for the study of the incentive effects of the tax and benefit system. Note that in the default configuration, neither of these is turned on. </para>
                         <section>
                               <title>Marginal Tax Rates</title>
                               <para>
                                     The procedure <function>Calculate_Marginal_Rate</function>
                                     in package <package>ZA.Model.Calculator</package>
                               is a very general routine for calculating the marginal tax rate of a household member. It works by incrementing the income of the member by some small amount and measuring the consequent change in household disposable income. This approach is computationally quite expensive, since for each parameter system it requires two model runs for each household member of interest, but has the advantage of being very simple and easy to maintain, since it requires no knowledge of the internal workings of the Tax and Benefit system. In practice, the SA system is probably sufficiently simple for marginal rates to be reliably worked out as a by-product of the normal calculations, simply by noting peoples ending income tax band and whether they are in scope for UIF, but this is not implemented. </para>
                         </section>
                         <!-- mrs -->
                         <section>
                               <title>Budget Constraints</title>
                               <para>
                                     Package <package>ZA.Model.Calculator.Budget_Constraints</package>
                                     implements a complete budget constraint generator ( <link linkend="duncan_and_stark_2000">(Duncan and Stark 2000)</link>
                               . For any individual, this computes how the disposable income of his household would change as his earnings change, from zero up to some arbitrarily large amount. Unlike alternative methods, it does this very precisely and in a computationally efficient way. This routine could be improved, however, if we had available data on either hours of work or hourly wage rates. </para>
                               <para> On the following page are two a simple examples of generated budget constraints, the first for a single person household with no other source of income, and the second for the head adult of a family with two children, also with no other income. </para>
                               <?hard-pagebreak?>
                               <table frame="none">
                                     <title>Simple Single Person Budget Constraint</title>
                                     <tgroup cols="3">
                                           <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
                                           <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="1*"/>
                                           <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="1*"/>
                                           <thead>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>Gross Income (Rands p.a.)</entry>
                                                       <entry>Household Net Income</entry>
                                                       <entry></entry>
                                                 </row>
                                           </thead>
                                           <tbody>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>0.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>0.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>No Benefits</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>54,200.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>53,658.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>Income Tax Starts. Marginal Rate is 1% (UIF)</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>132,000.01</entry>
                                                       <entry>116,676.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>25% income tax band MR now 26%</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>149,735.98</entry>
                                                       <entry>129,800.63</entry>
                                                       <entry>Upper Limit to UIF. Marginal Rate 25%</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>210,000.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>174,998.64</entry>
                                                       <entry>30% Income Tax Band</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>290,000.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>230,998.64</entry>
                                                       <entry>35% Income Tax</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>410,000.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>308,998.64</entry>
                                                       <entry>38% Income Tax</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>525,000.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>380,298.64</entry>
                                                       <entry>40% Income Tax</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>1,000,000.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>665,298.64</entry>
                                                       <entry>Top</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                           </tbody>
                                     </tgroup>
                               </table>
                               <table frame="none">
                                     <title>Family with two children, no other income</title>
                                     <tgroup cols="3">
                                           <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
                                           <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="1*"/>
                                           <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="1*"/>
                                           <thead>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>Gross Income (Rands p.a.)</entry>
                                                       <entry>Household Net Income</entry>
                                                       <entry></entry>
                                                 </row>
                                           </thead>
                                           <tbody>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>0.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>5,760.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>Child Support 2 * 240 * 12,5,760.00</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>54,200.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>59,418.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>Income Tax Starts.</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>57,600.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>62,172.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>Child Support Income Limit</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>57,600.01</entry>
                                                       <entry>56,412.01</entry>
                                                       <entry>Child Support Withdrawn: sharp fall in income</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>132,000.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>116,676.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>25% income tax band</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>149,736.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>129,800.64</entry>
                                                       <entry>UIT Upper Limit</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>210,000.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>174,998.64</entry>
                                                       <entry>30% Income Tax Band</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>290,000.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>230,998.64</entry>
                                                       <entry>33% Income Tax Band</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>410,000.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>308,998.64</entry>
                                                       <entry>38% Income Tax Band</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>525,000.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>380,298.64</entry>
                                                       <entry>40% Income Tax Band</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                                 <row>
                                                       <entry>1,000,000.00</entry>
                                                       <entry>665,298.64</entry>
                                                       <entry>Top</entry>
                                                 </row>
                                           </tbody>
                                     </tgroup>
                               </table>
                         </section>
                         <!-- bcs -->
                         </section>
                   <!-- labour supply -->
                   <?hard-pagebreak?>
                   <note>
                         <title>Calculation To Do</title>
                         <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> Uprating routine for parameters; </para>
                               </listitem>
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> Check: are some tax allowance parameters from 2008? </para>
                               </listitem>
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> Takeup based on probits run on IES 2005 raw data; </para>
                               </listitem>
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> Fix disability benefits under-reporting somehow (Calmar on population weights?) </para>
                               </listitem>
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> Much better modelling of deductions and allowances for income tax </para>
                               </listitem>
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> Better information on Cash Benefit Means Test: household income vs family income, other benefits included? </para>
                               </listitem>
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> Disability Grants Income Tax routine needs cleaned up; </para>
                               </listitem>
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> UIF: minimum levels included somehow? </para>
                               </listitem>
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> UIF: why the apparent under-reporting? </para>
                               </listitem>
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> Other near-taxes on wages included? </para>
                               </listitem>
                               <listitem>
                                     <para>
                                           Marginal Tax Rates as by-product of standard routines without calling <function>Calculate_Marginal_Rate</function>
                                     routine; and </para>
                               </listitem>
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> Simplify handling of incomes: too much duplication. </para>
                               </listitem>
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> Excise duties: more disaggregation. Explore adding income/price elasticities. Better information on base prices. </para>
                               </listitem>
                               <listitem>
                                     <para> Poverty: allow extreme/mild poverty; parameterise properly so child/adult amounts can vary; add equivalisation routine. </para>
                               </listitem>
                         </itemizedlist>
                   </note>
                   
             </section>
             <!-- calculation section -->
             <section>
                   <title>Output Routines and Optional Extras</title>
                   <para>
                         At the heart of the models output system are two extremely powerful general purpose tabulator packages: <package>Tabulator</package>
                         and <package>Costs_Tabulator</package>
                         . <package>Tabulator</package>
                         is a generic <footnote>
                               <para>
                                     In Ada, a generic package is a general purpose package that can at a later point be specialised to handle, for example, a particular data-type only. See <ulink url="http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Ada_Programming/Generics"></ulink>
                               </para>
                         </footnote>
                   package used to generate gain/lose and transition tables (transitions in and out of poverty, for example). In addition, it has a drill-down system that allows the user to examine the contents of particular cells: for example the proportion of those families who gain from a change that live in urban areas or who have a black head of household. Further, information on the location of individual households in the cell can be retrieved, so the user can find details examples of the kinds of households affected by a change. </para>
                   <para>
                         <package>Costs_Tabulator</package>
                         and <package>Poverty_Tabulator</package>
                   are more specialised tabulators designed to show budgetary information and poverty counts respectively. </para>
                   <para>
                         <package>Inequality_Generator</package>
                         is a generic package that generates lorenz curves and a variety of inequality measures. It is an almost direct translation into Ada of Python code written by <ulink url="http://poorcity.richcity.org">Goetz Kluge</ulink>
                         and available from <ulink url="http://luaforge.net/frs/download.php/181/inequality-1.3.4.py.html"> </ulink>
                   </para>
                   <para>
                         The initial verison of this model has been build for the Wider project <link linkend="wider_2009">(WIDER 2009)</link>
                         which has no need for much of the detail these packages can produce. Instead, specialisations of these packages have been built that produce restricted outputs in the required format for the Wider project. These are <package>Tabulator.Wider_IO</package>
                         , <package>Costs_Tabulator.Wider_IO</package>
                         , <package>Poverty_Tabulator.Wider_IO</package>
                         . The package <package>ZA.Model.Calculator.Wider_Output</package>
                   is used to define all the table instances used in the Wider edition and drive accumulation and output. </para>
             </section>
             <!-- output -->
       </section>
       <appendix>
         <title>Selected Source Listings</title>
       <section>
         <title>Household Data Types</title>
         <para>
         This is the package definition for
         </para>
         <xi:include
            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
            href="formatted_code/za-model_types.ads.xml" /> 

       </section>
       <section>
         <title>Household Definition</title>
         <para>
         This is the package definition for
         </para>
         <xi:include
            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
            href="formatted_code/za-model-data.ads.xml" /> 

       </section>
       <section>
         <title>Parameter Definitions</title>
         <para>
         This is the package definition for
         </para>
         <xi:include
            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
            href="formatted_code/za-model-params.ads.xml" /> 

       </section>
       <section>
         <title>Default Parameters</title>
         <para>
         This is the package definition for
         </para>
         <xi:include
            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
            href="formatted_code/za-model-params-defaults.adb.xml" /> 
       </section>
       
       </appendix>
       <!-- the model -->
       <bibliography id="za_model">
             <biblioentry id="wider_2009">
                   <abbrev>WIDER 2009</abbrev>
                   <title>WIDER - Simulation Models of 10 African Economies</title>
                   <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-08-15</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://models.wider.unu.edu"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="sassa_2009">
                   <abbrev>SASSA 2009</abbrev>
                   <title>SASSA - Grant Qualifying Requirements</title>
                   <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-08-15</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.sassa.gov.za/content.asp?id=1000000511"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="cape_gateway_2009">
                   <abbrev>Cape Gateway 2009</abbrev>
                   <title>GRANTS &amp;amp; PENSIONS</title>
                   <author>
                         <surname>Cape</surname>
                         <firstname>Gateway</firstname>
                   </author>
                   <pubdate>February 2009</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.capegateway.gov.za/eng/directories/services/11586"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="duncan_and_stark_2000">
                   <abbrev>Duncan and Stark 2000</abbrev>
                   <title>A recursive algorithm to generate piecewise linear budget contraints</title>
                   <authorgroup>
                         <author>
                               <surname>Duncan</surname>
                               <firstname>A</firstname>
                         </author>
                         <author>
                               <surname>Stark</surname>
                               <firstname>G</firstname>
                         </author>
                   </authorgroup>
                   <publisher>
                         <publishername>Instutue for Fiscal Studies</publishername>
                   </publisher>
                   <pubdate>2000</pubdate>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.nottingham.ac.uk/%7Elezad/downloads/wp0011.pdf"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="fry_and_stark_1993">
                   <abbrev>Fry and Stark 1993</abbrev>
                   <title>The Take-Up of Means-Tested Benefits, 1984-1990</title>
                   <authorgroup>
                         <author>
                               <surname>Fry</surname>
                               <firstname>V</firstname>
                         </author>
                         <author>
                               <surname>Stark</surname>
                               <firstname>G</firstname>
                         </author>
                   </authorgroup>
                   <publisher>
                         <publishername>Institute for Fiscal Studies, London</publishername>
                   </publisher>
                   <pubdate>1993</pubdate>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="sars_uif_quick_2007">
                   <abbrev>SARS UIF Quick Guide 2007</abbrev>
                   <title>AS-UIF-01 - Quick Reference Guide on UIF</title>
                   <corpauthor>South Africa Revenue Service (SARS)</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>2007</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.sars.gov.za/home.asp?pid=4150#AS-UIF-01 - Quick Reference Guide on UIF"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry>
                   <abbrev id="sars_exp_estimates_2009">SARS Expenditure Estimates 2009</abbrev>
                   <title>Budget 2009/10 Estimates of National Expenditure</title>
                   <corpauthor>South Africa Revenue Service (SARS)</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>February 2009</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.sars.gov.za/home.asp?pid=41119"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="sars_rev_estimates_2009">
                   <abbrev>SARS Revenue Estimates 2009</abbrev>
                   <title>Budget 2009/10 Estimates of National Revenue</title>
                   <corpauthor>South Africa Revenue Service (SARS)</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>February 2009</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.sars.gov.za/Tools/Documents/DocumentDownload.asp?FileID=42821"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="sars_proposals_2009">
                   <abbrev>SARS Budget Proposals 2009</abbrev>
                   <title>Budget 2009/10 Tax Proposals</title>
                   <corpauthor>South Africa Revenue Service (SARS)</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>February 2009</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.sars.gov.za/Tools/Documents/DocumentDownload.asp?FileID=42845"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="sars_budget_2009">
                   <abbrev>SARS Budget 2009</abbrev>
                   <title>Budget 2009/2010 Site</title>
                   <corpauthor>South Africa Revenue Service (SARS)</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>February 2009</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.sars.gov.za/home.asp?pid=41116"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="sars_excise_2006">
                   <abbrev>SARS Excise 2006</abbrev>
                   <title>Excise Duties and Levies - Reference Guide</title>
                   <corpauthor>South Africa Revenue Service (SARS)</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.sars.gov.za/home.asp?pid=4150#SC-ID-41"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="sars_comprehensive_2009">
                   <abbrev>SARS Comprehensive 2009</abbrev>
                   <title>Income Tax Comprehensive Guide 2009</title>
                   <corpauthor>South Africa Revenue Service (SARS)</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>July 2009</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.sars.gov.za/home.asp?pid=4150#Comprehensive Guide 2009"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="sars_income_tax_2009">
                   <abbrev>SARS Tax 2009</abbrev>
                   <title>Income Tax Overview</title>
                   <corpauthor>South Africa Revenue Service (SARS)</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>May 2009</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.sars.gov.za/home.asp?pid=4557"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="sars_tax_2006">
                   <abbrev>SARS Tax 2006</abbrev>
                   <title>Income Tax and the Individual</title>
                   <corpauthor>South Africa Revenue Service (SARS)</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>2006</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.sars.gov.za/home.asp?pid=4150#Income Tax and the Individual - 2006/07"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="sars_budget_review_2009">
                   <abbrev>SARS Budget Review 2009</abbrev>
                   <title>National Budget Review</title>
                   <corpauthor>South Africa Revenue Service (SARS)</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>February 2009</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.sars.gov.za/home.asp?pid=41118"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="sars_social_sec_2009">
                   <abbrev>SARS Social Sec 2009</abbrev>
                   <title>National Budget Review, Chapter 6: Social Security</title>
                   <corpauthor>South Africa Revenue Service (SARS)</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>February 2009</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.sars.gov.za/Tools/Documents/DocumentDownload.asp?FileID=42815"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="sars_excise_2007">
                   <abbrev>SARS Excise 2007</abbrev>
                   <title>SC-ID-16 - Quick Reference Guide to Excise Duties</title>
                   <corpauthor>South Africa Revenue Service (SARS)</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>2007</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.sars.gov.za/home.asp?pid=4150#SC-ID-16 - Quick Reference Guide to Excise Duties"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="sars_tax_stats_2008">
                   <abbrev>SARS Tax 2008</abbrev>
                   <title>Tax Statistics 2008</title>
                   <corpauthor>South Africa Revenue Service (SARS)</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.sars.gov.za/home.asp?pid=44114"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="sarpn">
                   <abbrev>SARPN 2004</abbrev>
                   <title>Fact Sheet: Poverty in South Africa</title>
                   <corpauthor>South African Regional Poverty Network</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>July 2004</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.sarpn.org.za/documents/d0000990/"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="treas_poverty">
                   <abbrev>Treasury 2007</abbrev>
                   <title>A National Poverty Line for South Africa</title>
                   <corpauthor>South African Treasury</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>February 2007</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.finance.gov.za/publications/other/povertyline/Treasury%20StatsSA%20poverty%20line%20discussion%20paper.pdf"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="treas_press">
                   <abbrev>Treasury Press 2009</abbrev>
                   <title>SA Treasury Press Releases - Monthly Press Releases - 2009</title>
                   <corpauthor>South African Treasury</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.treasury.gov.za/comm_media/press/monthly/monthly_2009.aspx"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="treas_2009">
                   <abbrev>Treasury 2009</abbrev>
                   <title>Statement of the National Revenue, Expenditure and Borrowing as at 30 June 2009</title>
                   <corpauthor>South African Treasury</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>July 2009</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.treasury.gov.za/comm_media/press/monthly/0908/press.pdf"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="IES_2005">
                   <abbrev>IES 2005</abbrev>
                   <title>Income and Expenditure Survey (IES) 2005 Home</title>
                   <corpauthor>Statistics South Africa</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.statssa.gov.za/ies/publications.asp"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="IES_2005A">
                   <abbrev>IES 2005A</abbrev>
                   <title>Income and expenditure of households 2005/2006 Metadata (Version 2)</title>
                   <corpauthor>Statistics South Africa</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="IES_2005B">
                   <abbrev>IES 2005B</abbrev>
                   <title>Coicop Code List</title>
                   <corpauthor>Statistics South Africa</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="IES_2005C">
                   <abbrev>IES 2005C</abbrev>
                   <title>P0100 - Income and expenditure of households 2005/2006: Statistical release</title>
                   <corpauthor>Statistics South Africa</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.statssa.gov.za/Publications/P0100/P01002005.pdf"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="IES_2005D">
                   <abbrev>IES 2005D</abbrev>
                   <title>Report-01-00-01 - Income and expenditure of households 2005/2006: Analysis of results</title>
                   <corpauthor>Statistics South Africa</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>2008</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://www.statssa.gov.za/Publications/Report-01-00-01/Report-01-00-012005.pdf"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
             <biblioentry id="UN2009">
                   <abbrev>UN 2009</abbrev>
                   <title>Classifications of Expenditure According to Purpose (COICOP): Detailed structure and explanatory notes</title>
                   <corpauthor>United Nations Statistics Division</corpauthor>
                   <pubdate>2009</pubdate>
                   <date role="cit">2009-07-26</date>
                   <biblioid class="uri">
                         <ulink url="http://unstats.un.org/unsd/cr/registry/regcst.asp?Cl=5"></ulink>
                   </biblioid>
             </biblioentry>
       </bibliography>
 </article>
